{"tossups": [{"question": "Ellsworth Bunker and R\u00b4omulo Betancourt helped negotiate the ownership of this structure, a development that Strom Thurmond responded to by noting \u201cwe bought it; we paid for it; it is ours.\u201dChief Sanitary Officer William Gorgas helped construct this structure, whose construction was advised by George Washington Goethals. The Torrijos-Carter [torr-HEE-yohs] Treaties transferred control of, for ten points, what waterway that connects the Atlantic and Pacific Ocean?", "answer": "<b> Panama</b> Canal", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Domenico Trezzini created a grid of canals for this city, which was constructed under Jean-Baptiste Alexandre le Blond. Fyodor Trepov flogged a political prisoner in this city, causing Vera Zasulich to shoot him. Dmitri Karakazov failed to kill a ruler in this city who was ultimately killed here by a bomb in 1881. In this city\u2019s Senate Square, rebels declared support for Grand Duke Constantine in the Decembrist Revolt. Alexander II was assassinated in, for ten points, what northern Russian city that was renamed for Lenin?", "answer": "<b> Saint Petersburg</b> (accept<b> Petrograd</b>; prompt on \u201cLeningrad\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This conflict\u2019s pivotal siege of Mahenge led the losing side to discard their castor oil and flee. During this conflict, the losing side rebeled against Carl Peters on the advice of Hongo, a snake spirit. The losers of this conflict joined Bokero after they were forced to produce cotton for export, leading to a devastating famine. For ten points, name this 1905 rebellion in German East Africa named for a medicine that was said to turn German bullets into water.", "answer": "<b> Maji Maji</b> Rebellion", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In a novel written in this language, an old man collects banned books obtained while working as a paper crusher. In another novel written in this language, a professor is robbed after protesting in Thailand and a female dog named after a Tolstoy novel is given as a gift to Tereza. After writing<em> The Garden Party</em>, an author in this language co-founded Charter 77 and gained political power in the Velvet Revolution. For ten points, name this language used by Bohumil Hrabal, Milan Kundera, and Vaclav Havel.", "answer": "<b> Czech</b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man believed he had killed Bernard \u201cLotsapoppa\u201d Crowe after he saw a news report about a dead Black Panther. This resident of the Spahn Movie Ranch was taught the guitar by Alvin \u201cCreepy\u201d Karpis, and he sent Bobby Beausoleil to kill music teacher Gary Hinman. Lynette \u201cSqueaky\u201d Fromme, a failed assassin of Gerald Ford, was a follower of this man, whose other followers carried out the Tate-LaBianca murders. The term \u201cHelter Skelter\u201d was used for an impending race war by, for ten points, what serial killer who led a cult in California in the 1960s?", "answer": "Charles Milles<b> Manson</b> Maddox", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "After this king\u2019s predecessor requested that Pope Clement XI denounce Jansenism, this king\u2019s advisor Cardinal Fleury persecuted the Jansenists. This king backed his father-in-law, Stanislaw I, in the War of the Polish Succession. The Pontcallec and Cellamare conspiracies targeted the regent for this ruler, Philippe II of Orleans. This king\u2019s chief mistress was Madame de Pompadour, and he ceded French Canada in the Treaty of Paris. For ten points, name this king whose successor was executed during the French Revolution.", "answer": "<b> Louis XV</b> [15]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In this country, Alberto Nisman was killed for investigating the 1994 bombing of a Jewish Community Center. Riots against hyperinflation in this country erupted during the presidency of Raul Alfonsin. The 1973 Ezeiza Massacre was perpetrated against the Montoneros in this country. A \u201cRainbow Tour\u201d of Europe was undertaken by actress Eva Duarte, this country\u2019s First Lady from 1946 to 1952. For ten points, name this country where Juan Peron ruled from Buenos Aires.", "answer": "<b> Argentina</b> (or<b> Argentine Republic</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Rick Kahn delivered a partisan eulogy for a politician from this state who died in a plane crash days before an election against Norm Coleman. That politician, Paul Wellstone, was replaced on this state\u2019s Senate ballot in 2000 by a man who had earlier criticized Gary Hart during a presidential primary with the slogan \u201cwhere\u2019s the beef?\u201d This state and Washington, DC were the only electoral votes carried by this state\u2019s native son in 1984. For ten points, name this home state of Walter Mondale.", "answer": "<b> Minnesota</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Leo Strauss argued that this man was the first modern thinker in his<em> Thoughts on</em> this philosopher. An essay by Frederick the Great rebuts this philosopher, who praised Cesare Borgia as the ideal ruler. This philosopher\u2019s major work of political philosophy was dedicated to his patron, Lorenzo de Medici, and argued that it is better to be feared than loved. For ten points, name this Italian renaissance philosopher who wrote<em> The Prince</em>.", "answer": "Niccolo<b> Machiavelli</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This author of the memoir</b><em><b> Standing Firm</b></em><b> was one of several Congressmen to decline Leo Ryan\u2019s fateful invitation to investigate Jonestown. This man attacked a \u201cpoverty of values\u201din a reference to TV character Murphy (+) Brown during a speech about the Rodney King</b> <b>riots. Lloyd Bentsen attacked this man as \u201cno (*)</b> Jack Kennedy\u201d in a vice presidential debate, and during the 1992 campaign, he was ridiculed for his misspelling of the word \u201cpotato.\u201d For ten points, name this Indiana native who served as Vice President for George H.W. Bush.", "answer": "James Danforth \u201cDan\u201d<b> Quayle</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Before funding this technology, Hugh Dowding demanded evidence and was impressed by the Daventry Experiment. America\u2019s knowledge of this technology improved after Henry</b> <b>Tizard\u2019s British delegation delivered a better (+)</b> <b>cavity magnetron. To hide the existence</b> <b>of this technology, a British propaganda campaign claimed that foods rich in Vitamin A, like (*) </b> carrots, improved night vision. The<em> Chain Home</em> stations used this technology to provide advance warning of Luftwaffe attacks. For ten points, name this detection technology that bounces radio waves off of incoming aircraft.", "answer": "<b> radar</b> (accept<b> radio detection and ranging</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>A plan to develop a city in this colony relied on a neighboring colony\u2019s</b><em><b> Grand Model</b></em><b> and used town wards consisting of four tything and four trust blocks. Benjamin Ingham and the</b> <b>Wesley brothers landed in this colony, where (+)</b> <b>Tomochichi of the Yamacraw and Mary</b> <b>Tomochichi of the Yamacraw and Mary</b> <b>Musgrove helped mediate peace. This colony\u2019s namesake experiment banned (*)</b> <b>Musgrove helped mediate peace. This colony\u2019s namesake experiment banned (*)</b> slavery, though a victory by this colony\u2019s forces at Bloody Marsh eventually led to the introduction of slavery. For ten points, name this southern colony, founded as a debtor\u2019s haven by James Oglethorpe, whose capital was Savannah.", "answer": "<b> Georgia</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}